Hello, class. My name is
Hugh Etlinger, and I'll be
working with you a fair
amount this year, introducing
you to the work of Dr.
Sutherland, both in BLT and the
cranial portion of your year,
and in treating systemic
problems in the hospital,
which has been a very
big part of my career,
something I feel like I have
something to say about. So
we're going to begin the
journey this year looking at
the work of Dr. Sutherland.
And in his technique, he called
balanced ligamentous tension.
So I want to go through,
you know, the principles
of this technique really
requires you to understand
the anatomic and
physiological basis for it.
So we'll look at that
and the concept of a
ligamentous articular
mechanism, how important sensing
is, developing your
sensing skills. That's one
of my, I think, one of
the more important things
I'm going to try to bring
to you this year. And
then Dr. Sutherland's
concept of natural agencies.
BLT is not so much a
technique that you perform
as it is an investigation
of the body's physiology
and bringing that to bear to
actually make the correction.
And the idea that BLT is not
just an indirect technique.
It's kind of
pigeonholed as that in a
lot of areas of our
profession, including
the sort of overall
discussion of schools.
But I'll talk about
that because I think
that's a limited view of
Dr. Sutherland's work.
So Dr. Sutherland
was a graduate of
the American School of
Osteopathy. That was Dr. Still's
school. And that was in
1900. So the school formed
in 1892. And up in through
the early 1900s, 1903, 04,
you know, the school was
very small, had 25 or 30
students. And so it was
really a mentorship with Dr.
Still. And Dr. Sutherland
was there. He started in
1898. And so he very
directly credits Dr. Still,
not only for his approach,
but his philosophy and
thinking and most of what
he did. So this is a quote
from Dr. Sutherland. We
will be looking at this in
parts. So we'll begin with
his thought that Dr. Still
has taken my hand in his
and allowed me to feel.
That was part of
the mentorship or
apprenticeship with Dr.
Still, is he would actually
do hands-over-hands
teaching, which is
something that I think
is still critical.
And any time in the lab,
you have an opportunity
to get one of the
instructors to put their
hands over yours and
actually help you to
experience the treatment,
particularly with BLT.
It's really of incredible
value. Once you
have that experience,
then you have a much
better idea of what
you're looking for.
And that kind of brings
us to an idea that
I think is critically
important in the
passing on of osteopathic
information and
legacy is that we do
have this lineage.
So we have Dr. Still, who
was the originator. And
then Dr. Sutherland was his
student and was profoundly
influenced by the time
that he had with Dr. Still.
In the middle here is
Dr. Ann Wales. And she's
an important part of this
picture because she was
likewise influenced by Dr.
Sutherland. And then down
here in the corner is a study
group. This is Dr. Wales
here in the center that
grew up around her. And she
spent a good bit of time
passing on that information to
a number of us. So, you
know, Ann was, this is Ann
here, and she was not only
his student, but part of his
teaching faculty for 10 years.
She became a close friend
of his. And then starting
in about the mid-1980s
or late 1980s, she met some
young students, a study group
formed around her, and she
spent 18 years until she
died in 2005. And I was
privileged to be part of that
group for 15 years. I spent
quite a bit of time with
her, both with the group
and in her home. So I feel
like that's my, you know, my
position to be here and try
and help you to understand
what I learned from her.
So by introduction, you
know, Dr. Still was not one
for teaching technique. He
taught osteopathy, which
is a much bigger picture
and one that's really hard
to grasp while you're in
class because there's so many
techniques to learn and
mechanics to learn and basic
anatomy. And so hopefully
I can give you a taste
of that as we work together
across, I don't know, six
or seven classes that I'll
have with you this year.
And that osteopathy is really
founded in philosophy
and principles.
And techniques just sort
of naturally arrive. Dr.
Still was very adamant
about that. And he didn't
teach his students technique.
He taught them anatomy
and taught them how to go
from their understanding
of physiology and then
figure it out. And I think
one of the more important
things that I hope to get
across to you is that
osteopathy is medicine. It's
not learning techniques
that you pull out of your
bag and throw at this or
that problem or complaint.
It's medicine. It's
understanding a patient's
problem. It's designing a
treatment plan. And then
including your understanding
of how structure is impacting
this problem, whether
it's a pain complaint or
or an ICU patient and
designing a treatment
plan. And that makes
it medicine. And
I think that's an
important distinction.
And then something that
I am going to be harping
on, I think OMM class can
become, you know, about
learning things to do.
And, you know, certainly
techniques are things to
do, but ultimately the
skill involved in practicing
osteopathic manipulative
medicine is sensing. It's
really not about what
you do. It's about what
you feel. And as such,
then OMM really becomes
diagnostic art, something where
you can use your hands as
a diagnostic instrument and
really come to understand
your patient a lot more
clearly. And hopefully today's
talk will be a beginning
in that sort of vein to give
you something to think about
as you go into lab and work
to develop your skills.
Dr. Sutherland was pretty
clear about that. If
you understand the
mechanism, the treatment is
simple. In other words,
it's really about diagnosis.
Dr. Shiawitz, and I hope that
Many of you recognize
the name Stan Shiawitz.
He was my mentor
at NYIT when it was
called NICOM. He was
my department chair.
He used to say, he
was from Brooklyn,
I could teach a
chimpanzee to treat.
The job of the physician
is to make the diagnosis.
In other words, that's the
hard part. And the development
of your osteopathic skills
can be a huge asset,
regardless of what specialty
you go on to practice.
Being able to include
structure in your evaluation of
your patient is a really
big thing. And I hope to
share a lot of my experiences
with you over the years.
And so just a few more
introductory thoughts. you know,
thinking versus tinkering.
That was one of Dr.
Sutherland's favorite phrases,
you know, tinkering kind
of being, okay, I find a
boo-boo, I fix it, you know.
You'll see a lot of, I see
a lot of students, well,
you know, the patient has
this disease, and then
I find, you know, this C3
dysfunction and this T2,
and I'll just use this
technique or that technique.
And really what it should be
is, okay, here's a patient
with such and such a problem
and then structurally
you know they have a postural
decompensation that's at
the root of their back
pain complaint or they have
segmental facilitation that's
adding to their you know
tachycardia and and whatever
else it is understanding that
thinking part of OMM the
medicine part. In terms of
learning techniques, I always
try to design my labs to
show you each technique is
something new to feel, learning
to sense at a greater depth,
learning to differentiate
fascial strains from muscle
tension, from articular
strains. And then in terms
of doing versus sensing.
I think, you know,
particularly as we learn
complex techniques, you
know, we pay attention to
the patient when we're
making our diagnosis. I
see this, I see that. Okay,
now here's my technique
and I'm going to do this
and then I turn them
this way and I put my
hand here and I do this
and all of a sudden it's
about what I'm doing.
Whereas really the question
is not what are you doing?
How is the patient responding
to what you're doing?
And if you can learn to
continue that sort of perceptive
sense as you go to your
treatments, whether
it's a complex mechanical
treatment or a simple
exaggeration, indirect kind
of technique, that sensing can
be critical. I mean, imagine.
If you could, as you're
approaching a barrier
to do a thrust, realize,
you know, this barrier just
doesn't feel right compared
to the barriers that I felt
when that thrust worked
and maybe find an alternative
before you kind of
slam down and don't get
the thing to go and the
patient kind of goes into
spasm and writhes in pain.
And, you know, those things
can happen, but only if
you're paying attention.
And then within that paying
attention is the idea that
there's actually powers
within the patient, a potency
within the patient that
is going to be the motive
force, particularly as we
study BLT, and that that
is something you can see.
And we'll be talking about
that quite a bit as we go
along. So this idea that,
you know, treatment is an
extended diagnosis that you
continue to sense, looking for
clues in the response of
the patient that will guide
your treatment, and that
that's what you should learn
to pay attention to. That
is not an easy thing to do.
I'll say that right out.
That is a really, really
challenging skill, but
one that's going to
make all of your technique
a whole lot better.
So Dr. Wales had a bit to
say about this. She said,
a physician who practices
osteopathy must administer
the treatment with his
own manual operations,
that's what she called
techniques, or he will not be
aware of the information
that the process discloses.
She could add to that
that that information will
only be disclosed if
you're paying attention.
She also said this, as the
treatment program progresses,
his experience as operator
and the continuing
diagnostic interpretation
as his guide inspires this
creation. And so the idea
that as you begin a technique,
it's just an initiation,
but it's the clues that come
from the patient's response
that allow you to adapt
that technique, even in the
middle of performing it,
adjusting it. again, you know,
this idea that osteopathy
individualizes. So this
is in the moment within
a technique, you individualize
based on the response
of the patient's tissues
as you start the process of
setting up that technique.
And it makes, certainly it
makes it more difficult,
but also much more exciting.
And with the same skill
level, just the idea that
this is what you're doing
will make your technique
better as you're developing
your skills. And so as we
look at this process, here's
Dr. Sutherland involved.
Is he making a diagnosis or
is he giving a treatment?
And the answer is yes,
that's what he's doing. He's
diagnosing and treating all
kind of in the same time.
And so, again, this is
something that is going
to make your treatments
more effective. I also
want to emphasize that
it's a treatment plan.
It's not just finding
and fixing somatic
dysfunctions. It's understanding
their role in whatever
problem the patient's
bringing to you. And
then once you get into
the treatment, it's about
individualizing that treatment
plan. So in osteopathy,
I would say, thankfully,
there is no protocol,
there's no algorithm, there's
what you find, there's
a starting point for a
treatment, and then even
there, there's the
adaptation of that treatment.
And so something that Dr.
Wales always used to say
that is one of my
favorite quotes going in,
particularly the way medicine
is practiced today, she would
say, no two patients with
the same disease will
ever present exactly the
same way. And no one patient
with the same disease
ever presents exactly the
same on any two different
visits. So it's always
individualization is a
constant process from the
microscopic to the
macroscopic and really makes
osteopathy a much more exciting
way to practice for me.
So one of the most important
concepts that I think
went into the development
of balanced ligamentous
tension, and this is not
a myofascial technique,
this is from dr sutherland
he said in describing
spinal lesions i prefer the
term ligamentous articular
strain for lesions and
for lesions in the cranium
membranous articular
strains we'll get to the
cranial stuff moving forward
in the year spinal lesions
include the ligaments as
well as the joints and
the cranial lesions include
the membranes lesion is
the word they used for
somatic dysfunction, as well
as the articulation. So
you don't really have an
articular strain because
the way I interpret this,
an articulation, the
articular surfaces simply
define the planes of
motion that are allowed.
All of the tension, whether
it be the anatomical barrier
or the pathological barrier,
is going to come from
the ligaments. And so the
ligaments and the joints
cooperate to create a
ligamentous articular mechanism.
And therefore, and
something I hope to impress
you with as you learn
about Dr. Sutherland
and his work, was
just how thoughtful he
was about his terms.
He created the term
ligamentous articular
strain as his diagnosis.
so I was asked to include
some discussion of ligamentous
articular strain which has
been written up by a group
as a technique and I feel
like that is a it's based
on their understanding of
Dr. Sutherland's work that
was from a study group that
grew around Dr. Roland Becker
who was another of Dr.
Sutherland's students and
certainly a great osteopath.
And my personal opinion was
if you asked him what
he was doing, he would
say balanced ligamentous
tension, but they
decided to create
ligamentous articular
strain. I think it's a
poor choice of language.
And I will go into a
little more detail to try
to help you understand
what Dr. Brett Becker
brought that was somewhat
unique, you know, in
osteopathy, we're taught
anatomy, we're taught
principles, we're taught
to think individually.
And so everybody works a
little bit differently.
And that can be very
frustrating as a student.
But, you know, to be
encouraged to work that way and
learn that way and think
and become an individual,
I think is one of the hallmarks
of osteopathic medicine
and really important.
Okay, so a ligamentous
articular mechanism. So the
ligaments in their tension
regulate the movements in
the spinal articulations as
check agents to the voluntary
muscular action. They
might be called reciprocal
tension ligaments. So Dr.
Sutherland is building
a model of the skeleton,
the ligaments and the
joints, as something that
functions independent
of the neuromuscular
agents that move those
articulations voluntarily.
And this is a really
fundamental concept that he
developed as he studied
anatomy and explored his
technique. and it's
something really important.
Again,
balanced ligamentous
tension is not a myofascial
technique. It reflects that
concept of a skeletal system.
So Dr. Wales interpreted
that for us by saying the
neuromuscular system provides
the power and control
for the voluntary mobility
of our skeletal system.
Underlying this, however,
is an involuntary
action within the
skeletal system itself.
Mechanical problems in
this action are the first
consideration of a working
diagnosis for an osteopath.
And so we'll be looking
at that concept of not a
neuromuscular skeletal
system, but a skeletal system
that functions independently.
And obviously, then
muscular action is not
considered in part of that.
It's then involuntary
motion that is going to be
operating that skeletal
system. And we'll be
exploring that as we go
along. So what are those
involuntary motions? What
Dr. Wales would call the
powers within the patient's
body, those natural
agencies. So again, back
to that initial quote,
you know, Dr. Still has
taken my hand in his
and allowed me to feel
the lesion as it was
being exaggerated. And
then as the natural
agencies pulled the
bones back into place.
And so, you know, that
was a very big part of Dr.
Still's concept and principles.
The most any physician
can do for a patient is
render operative the forces
within the body itself,
those natural agencies.
Dr. Sutherland said, we
do not force anything into
place in the reduction
of the lesion. We have
something more potent than
our own force working always
in the patient towards
the direction of normal.
osteopathy is a science
with possibilities as great
as the magnitude of the
heavens. It is a science
dealing with the natural forces
of the body. These forces
within the patient are
greater than any blind
force that can be safely
brought to bear from without.
And so the idea of the
natural agencies in the
body, and what would those
possibly be? So as we
continue the year and we
learn about his cranial
concept, we'll learn about
the primary respiratory
mechanism, which is a
involuntary motion that moves
every part of our body and
can be brought to bear.
But there's a lot more than
that. I think some people
kind of pigeonhole this
whole idea as to, well,
this is Dr. Sutherland's
cranial concept. One of my
favorite quotes from Anne
is, respiratory cooperation
is always with us in
operations designed to utilize
the powers within the
patient's body. So breathing.
And it's very common to
find in a bad somatic
dysfunction that you actually
don't feel that area move
with breathing. Now, if
you're in the ribs, that can
be very obvious. You know,
if you're in the ankle,
that can be incredibly
subtle, but it's still there.
And if you find that this
part doesn't move with
breathing and then use your
positioning to all of a
sudden restore breathing, all
of a sudden that breathing
can actually work that
articulation free and help
restore both normal
relations and normal tension.
There's really quite
a large variety.
And I think
for me, one of the most
important ideas is that
these actions are things
you can learn to sense.
And as you sense them, you
start to realize not only
what is helping this area come
back to to normal function
to reduce that somatic
dysfunction but you know maybe
what was wrong with it in
the first place it wasn't
just that it was tight it
was that it was limiting our
physiology because we look
at these inherent forces
so you know when we do the
counter strain model we talk
about the muscle spindle so
actually the joint capsules
have just as many proprioceptors
as the muscles do.
And when there's tension
in those ligaments,
there will be tension
in the tissues
surrounding. And sometimes
the best way to get at
that tension is not
to work through the
muscles, but to work
through the articulation.
Those joint capsules,
ligaments are also filled with
nociceptors. And nociceptors,
as you'll learn when
you learn about facilitated
segments, will also
produce local tension at
that segment that will limit
motion and alter position.
And as you position to ease,
it's not just the painful
muscles, it's not just
the counter strain model,
but those nociceptors in
the joint capsules are also
very tender and you position
to ease, and you turn down
those nociceptors, and
the articulation then will
start to reset itself.
There's a lot of
circulatory conditions.
Commonly,
you know, the veins and
lymphatics are very pliable,
easily compressed, and so
So somatic dysfunction can
very often congest the
tissue because it can't drain
out. And as you position to
a point of balanced tension,
you know, you might
feel a congested tissue
decongest, and that might be
part of the overall correction
at that segment. But, you
know, the arterial supply
also can be, and you can
have an area that really is
kind of dry and poorly
perfused. And you can feel it
fill what Dr. Still used
to call the rivers of life.
Even just as you
position, all of a sudden,
there's something happening,
kind of circulation.
So, you know, in regard to
that, one of my favorite
quotes from Dr. Still, you
know, we suffer two causes,
the want of supply and the
burden of dead deposits.
And again, those aren't just
concepts. These are things
that you can learn to feel
and watch change through
a technique if you're
sensing, if your goal in
performing the technique is
to sense what's going on. And
then finally, microcirculation.
And this is part of
almost all great osteopathic
philosophy is that somatic
dysfunction ultimately can
affect right down to the
cellular level, cellular
exchange of oxygen and
nutrients and that sort of
cellular respiration, which is
also very sensitive to
tension. Uh, it's, uh, it
depends on those, uh, small
inherent motions that can be,
uh, really interfered with
by somatic dysfunction,
uh, and learning to feel
sort of in that microscopic,
um, uh, situation when
you're working locally,
uh, those changes are
also things that you
can learn to feel and
also things that therefore
can be restored with
osteopathic technique,
which to me then, again,
is a lot more than
just sort of loosening
up a tight spot per se.
And this is a quote from
Dr. Sutherland, who then
said, well, the goal of an
osteopathic treatment is
to improve the interchange
of fluids of the body across
all interfaces. And that
really kind of speaks to
that concept of
microcirculation. And so as you
learn to look at somatic
dysfunction, I'd encourage you
to expand beyond tight
and stiff and look at the
impact of that tight and
stiff spot on a variety of
inherent motions, breathing,
pulse, the primary
respiratory mechanism, the
sense of congestion. And then
you'll see the impact of
that somatic dysfunction
being more than just a
tight spot or a sore spot or
any of those kind of things
that we typically think
about, but really something
that participates in
physiology and sometimes in
a very consequential way.
This is something we'll
look at as we get into the
systemic part. So now let's
get down to brass tacks.
We already know that our
goal is going to be to
explore those natural agencies,
that the treatment will
depend on them. Let's talk
about how we get to that
place where those natural
agencies come to bear.
And again, you will be
learning techniques, but I'd
encourage you to look past
those techniques, look beneath
them, try to understand
the principles. and then
be able to adapt ultimately
when you come to situations
where that technique either
doesn't fit your patient
or it doesn't fit your,
you know, these techniques
are designed by someone 6
'2", you're 5'5", whatever it
is, if you understand the
principles, you really can
design adaptations that
apply the same principle. Dr.
Sutherland again called
his technique principle
balanced ligamentous tension
and balanced membranous tension
in the head because the
head has dural membranes
whereas the body has ligaments
in the joint capsules.
And here we'll finally
come back to this statement
and look at this
statement here, allowed
me to feel the lesion as
it was being exaggerated.
So exaggeration was the
term used in the old
days for indirect
method. So this would be
basically indirect
technique. And I think again,
BLT is considered an
indirect technique. I didn't
learn it that way. I learned
that there's actually
a variety of different
ways you can position.
And that some of
them are direct,
some of them are indirect.
Exaggeration or indirect
is the most common. But
ultimately, the idea
is that you're going to
achieve a point of balance
membranous or ligamentous
tension. and that what
that point of balanced
tension is going to do
is it is going to engage
those powers within the
patient and that they are
going to be what ultimately
makes the correction.
So part of the group
that worked with
Dr. Sutherland came
up with a definition
as the point in the range
of motion of an articulation
where the ligaments and
membranes are poised
between the normal tension
present throughout the
free range of motion and
the increased tension
preceding the strain. And
so, you know, ultimately
that is a very simple
concept, but there really is a
great depth to it because
what you can learn to
sense about how the body's
working through the use
of balanced ligamentous
tension and the development
of your sensing skills
is really quite profound.
And again, sometimes
exaggeration or indirect is the
way to go and other times,
really not so much. So I had
a difficult time understanding
the concept of balanced
ligamentous tension in the
direct direction. And so
in Dr. Whale's house, she
had a book that had these two
diagrams. So this would be,
you know, my dysfunction,
tight on one side, loose
on the other side. And
pretty obvious, if I close
this lid a little bit,
I'll slack this side,
and now I've got balanced
tension. But I also can
lift this slack side,
bring up the tension,
and also balance the
tension. And so again,
that idea that that point
just before tension
increases in dysfunction,
once I'm at that
point, I can either
back off it and slack it,
or I can lean into it.
So when might I decide
to lean into it? Well,
you know, truthfully,
I work on some really
sick patients. I
have patients who are
breathing really
shallow, their pulse is
weak, their primary
respiratory mechanism is
inhibited or weak, they
don't have a lot of inherent
forces. So just exaggerating,
just slacking the
tissues doesn't do it. You
don't really feel those
inherent forces or powers
within the patient come up.
And so at that point, I
might lean in a little bit.
And now I'm adding some
energy into that equation and
using that to sort of stir
those tissues to action.
So direct action, yes,
but not like I'm going to
engage a barrier and force
my way through it. That's
not the point. Here,
I'm going to get to the
barrier and lean into it a
little bit and really try
to stir those tissues
to action to bring forth
those powers within the
patient or natural agencies.
And used that way, it
can be very effective
and still stays true
to Dr. Sutherland's
principle of utilizing
the powers within the
patient's body. So
it's a different way of
thinking about direct
action. And ultimately,
so this would be
exaggeration. You know, this
part here, the top one
here is side bend to the
left. So I side bend
it further to the left.
This one further to the right.
Indirect. I
exaggerate the lesion.
Or direct action. Now I'm
bringing them towards,
but again, I'm not looking
to overcome the barrier.
Simply engage it and add
in some energy to try to
stir those powers within
the patients to action.
Disengagement, this is
a very common one, one
that I use a lot. So
I'm not necessarily,
this is side bend to
the left. I'm not side
bending it to the right.
I'm just taking these
two parts and drawing
them apart directly.
I'm bringing up tension, so
I consider it a subset of
direct action, but
disengagement was described by,
these were all described by
Dr. Sutherland as different
ways that he found to
achieve a point of balanced
ligamentous tension. Opposing
physiologic motion, I'm not
going to spend a lot of
time on. It's a little
complicated. It's one that he
described mostly for complex
trauma situations and really
unphysiological strains,
but that was one he described.
And then molding, which
typically we use in babies
with kind of funny shaped
head, this would be the
classic parallelogram head of
a baby. But really, molding
is something that you can
use when you find strain,
not so much between the bones
at the joints, but within
the bone itself, in which
case, it's really about
the shape of the bone. And
that's something that we
can talk about. And then one
last thing I want to bring
up. So in terms of trying to
give you a sense of ligamentous
articular strain, so
Dr. Becker was a truly a
brilliant osteopath. Now, he
used a lot of compression
that he'd add in as, again,
not necessarily his main
concept in positioning or
bringing tissues to a point
of balanced tension, but
as something he added in
to, again, try to stir those
tissues to life. I'd be
incredibly surprised if Dr.
Sutherland didn't also
introduce compression. And it
really isn't necessarily
something that's different.
But a lot of the
ligamentous articular strain
techniques include
compression, adding compression
to your overall point
of balance tension.
And that, I think,
comes from Dr. Becker,
because that was something
that he did as he went
and explored the
techniques in his own way.
You can, like in
other techniques.
Directing the tide is something
that we probably won't
get to this year. But
once you get to a point of
balance, there are some
other things that you can do.
Respiratory assistance,
take a breath and
hold it, take a breath
out and hold it.
Postural assistance,
you know, position your
body this way to sort of
just things you can do
to enhance that point of
balance tension. Also,
you know, stir those
involuntary motions to action.
And then again, that this is
part of an overall treatment
plan. I can't emphasize that
enough. We're physicians.
Ann used to say, we are
physicians who practice
osteopathy. It doesn't mean
that we're body workers.
So always a diagnosis and
an understanding of the role
of the somatic dysfunctions
in that diagnosis, coming
up with a treatment plan
that includes frequency,
that includes endpoints, all
of those things are really
critical to practicing
osteopathy. So in conclusion,
the best line that any lecturer
can ever say in a lecture,
so balanced membranous and
ligamentous tension is the
treatment principle of Dr.
Sutherland. The idea is
that you bring an area of
strain at the ligaments,
not the neuromuscular system,
to a point of balanced
tension, which is a position
where those inherent
forces of the body come to
bear. as you learn to recognize
that, you will recognize
that many somatic
dysfunctions really do limit
those inherent forces. That's
probably why they don't
self-correct to begin with,
and that can really lead
you to a far more in-depth
understanding of the nature
of the dysfunction and
more importantly, the
physiological consequences.
And that once you hit that
point of balance, you don't
look at the clock for 90
seconds, you pay attention.
And that's the window.
That's such a window into
body physiology. You can
observe what happens as that
articulation or area of
strain corrects and really is
a remarkable way to study
body physiology. So that's
all for today, and I will
be seeing you in the future.